by sharing a poem
بمشاركة قصيدة
written by my friend from Malawi,
كتبتها صديقتي من مالاوي
Eileen Piri.
إلين بيري
Eileen is only 13 years old,
إلين عمرها 13 سنة فقط
but when we were going through the collection of poetry that we wrote,
ولكن عندما كنا نمر على المجموعة الشعرية التي كتبناها
I found her poem so interesting,
وجدت قصيدتها مهمة جدا
so motivating.
ومحفزة جدا
So I'll read it to you.
لهذا سأقرؤها لكم
She entitled her poem "I'll Marry When I Want."
عنونت قصيدتها "سأتزوج عندما أريد"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"I'll marry when I want.
"سأتزوج عندما أريد
My mother can't force me to marry.
أمي لا تستطيع إجباري على الزواج
My father cannot force me to marry.
أبي لا يستطيع إجباري على الزواج
My uncle, my aunt,
عمّي عمّتي
my brother or sister,
أخي أو أختي
cannot force me to marry.
لا يستطيعون إجباري على الزواج
No one in the world
لا أحد في العالم
can force me to marry.
يستطيع إجباري على الزواج
I'll marry when I want.
سأتزوج عندما أريد
Even if you beat me,
حتى وإن ضربتني
even if you chase me away,
و طردتني
even if you do anything bad to me,
و آذيتني
I'll marry when I want.
فسأتزوج عندما أريد
I'll marry when I want,
سأتزوج عندما أريد
but not before I am well educated,
ولكن ليس قبل أن أتعلم جيدا
and not before I am all grown up.
وليس قبل أن يكتمل نموي
I'll marry when I want."
سأتزوج عندما أريد"
This poem might seem odd,
قد تبدو هذه القصيدة غريبة
written by a 13-year-old girl,
كتبتها طفلة في سن 13
but where I and Eileen come from,
ولكن في البلد الذي أنتمي له أنا وإلين
this poem, which I have just read to you,
هذه القصيدة التي قرأت لكم للتوّ
is a warrior's cry.
هي صرخة محارب
I am from Malawi.
أنا من مالاوي
Malawi is one of the poorest countries,
مالاوي من أفقر الدول
very poor,
فقيرة جدا
where gender equality is questionable.
حيث المساواة بين الجنسين أمر مريب
Growing up in that country,
وأنا أترعرع في هذا البلد
I couldn't make my own choices in life.
لم أستطع التحكم في قرارتي المصيرية
I couldn't even explore
لم أستطع حتى اكتشاف
personal opportunities in life.
الفرص الشخصية في الحياة
I will tell you a story
سأروي لكم قصة
of two different girls,
عن فتاتين مختلفتين
two beautiful girls.
فتاتين جميلتين
These girls grew up
نشأت هاتان الفتاتان
under the same roof.
تحت السقف نفسه
They were eating the same food.
كانتا تأكلان نفس الطعام
Sometimes, they would share clothes,
وتتشاركان أحيانا ذات الملابس
and even shoes.
وحتى الأحذية
But their lives ended up differently,
ولكن حياتهم انتهت بشكل مختلف،
in two different paths.
في مسارين مختلفين
The other girl is my little sister.
الفتاة الأخرى هي أختي الصغيرة
My little sister was only 11 years old
أختي الصغيرة كان عمرها 11 سنة
when she got pregnant.
عندما أصبحَت حاملا
It's a hurtful thing.
إنه أمر مؤذٍ
Not only did it hurt her, even me.
لم يؤذها لوحدها بل حتى أنا
I was going through a hard time as well.
كنت أعيش وقتا عصيبا كذلك
As it is in my culture,
كما هو الحال في ثقافتي،
once you reach puberty stage,
بمجرد وصولك إلى مرحلة البلوغ،
you are supposed to go to initiation camps.
يصبح من المفترض ذهابك لمخيمات التأهيل
In these initiation camps,
في مخيمات التأهيل هذه
you are taught how to sexually please a man.
يعلمونك كيفية إرضاء الرجل جنسيا
There is this special day,
حيث ذلك اليوم المميز
which they call "Very Special Day"
الذي يسمونه "يوم خاص جدا"
where a man who is hired by the community
حيث الرجل الذي تم التعاقد معه من قبل المجتمع
comes to the camp
يأتي إلى المخيم
and sleeps with the little girls.
وينام مع الفتيات الصغيرات
Imagine the trauma that these young girls
تخيلوا الصدمة التي تمرّ منها
go through every day.
الفتيات الصغيرات كل يوم
Most girls end up pregnant.
أغلب الفتيات ينتهي بهن الأمر وهن حوامل
They even contract HIV and AIDS
وقد يصبن بفيروس ومرض الإيدز
and other sexually transmitted diseases.
وغيرها من الأمراض المنقولة جنسيا
For my little sister, she ended up being pregnant.
بالنسبة لأختي الصغيرة انتهى بها الأمر حاملا
Today, she's only 16 years old
اليوم تبلغ من العمر 16 سنة
and she has three children.
ولديها 3 أطفال
Her first marriage did not survive,
زواجها الأول لم يستمر
nor did her second marriage.
ولا زواجها الثاني
On the other side, there is this girl.
وفي الجانب الآخر هناك فتاة
She's amazing.
إنها مذهلة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I call her amazing because she is.
أقول مذهلة لأنـّها كذلك
She's very fabulous.
إنها رائعة للغاية
That girl is me. (Laughter)
هذه الفتاة هي أنا (ضحك)
When I was 13 years old,
عندما كنت في سن الثالثة عشر
I was told, you are grown up,
قيل لي " لقد نضجت
you have now reached of age,
كنت قد بلغت الآن ذلك التأهيل،
you're supposed to go to the initiation camp.
ويفترض بك الذهاب لمخيمات البدء"
I was like, "What?
قلت:"ماذا؟
I'm not going to go to the initiation camps."
أنا لن أذهب إلى مخيمات التأهيل"
You know what the women said to me?
هل تعلمون بماذا ردّت علي النساء؟
"You are a stupid girl. Stubborn.
"أنت فتاة غبية و عنيدة
You do not respect the traditions of our society, of our community."
أنت لا تحترمين تقاليد جماعتنا ومجتمعنا "
I said no because I knew where I was going.
قلت لا لأنني عرفت أين كنت ذاهبة
I knew what I wanted in life.
وعرفت ماذا أريد من الحياة
I had a lot of dreams as a young girl.
كان لدي الكثير من الأحلام كفتاة شابة
I wanted to get well educated,
أردت الحصول على قدر جيد من التعليم
to find a decent job in the future.
للحصول على وظيفة لائقة في المستقبل
I was imagining myself as a lawyer,
كنت أتخيل نفسي كمحامية
seated on that big chair.
تجلس على كرسيها الكبير
Those were the imaginations that
كانت هذه هي التخيلات التي
were going through my mind every day.
تمر بذهني كل يوم
And I knew that one day,
وعلمت أنه في يوم ما
I would contribute something, a little something to my community.
وأود أن أساهم في شيء، ولو كان أمرا بسيطا لمجتمعي.
But every day after refusing,
ولكن كل يوم بعد الرفض
women would tell me,
النساء يقلن لي:
"Look at you, you're all grown up. Your little sister has a baby.
"أنظري إلى نفسك لقد كبرت وأختك الصغيرة لها طفل
What about you?"
ماذا عـنـك أنتِ؟"
That was the music that I was hearing every day,
كانت هذه هي الموسيقى التي أسمعها كل يوم
and that is the music that girls hear every day
وهي الموسيقى التي تسمعها الفتيات كل يوم
when they don't do something that the community needs them to do.
عندما لا يفعلن ما يطلبه منهن المجتمع
When I compared the two stories between me and my sister,
عندما قارنت بين قصّتينا أنا وأختي
I said, "Why can't I do something?
قلتُ: "لماذا لا أفعل شيئا!
Why can't I change something that has happened for a long time
لماذا لا يمكنني تغيير شيء ما حدث لفترة طويلة
in our community?"
في مجتمعنا
That was when I called other girls
كان ذلك عندما كلمت فتيات أخريات
just like my sister, who have children,
مثل أختي ممن لديهن أطفال
who have been in class but they have forgotten how to read and write.
كنّ في الصف لكنهن نسين القراءة والكتابة
I said, "Come on, we can remind each other
قلت:" هيا بوسعنا أن نذكر بعضنا البعض
how to read and write again,
كيف نكتب ونقرأ مرة أخرى
how to hold the pen, how to read, to hold the book."
كيف نمسك القلم كيف نقرأ كيف نمسك كتابا
It was a great time I had with them.
كان وقتا رائعا قضيته معهن
Nor did I just learn a little about them,
ليس فقط أنني تعلمت القليل حولهن
but they were able to tell me their personal stories,
ولكن كنّ قادرات على أن يحكين قصصهن الشخصية
what they were facing every day
وما واجهنه كل يوم
as young mothers.
كأمهات شابات
That was when I was like,
كان ذلك عندما كنت مثل،
'Why can't we take all these things that are happening to us
لماذا لا يمكن أن نأخذ كل هذه الأشياء التي تحدث لنا
and present them and tell our mothers, our traditional leaders,
ونعرضها ونخبر أمهاتنا وزعماءنا التقليديين
that these are the wrong things?"
أن هذه تصرفات خاطئة؟"
It was a scary thing to do,
كان أمرا مخيفا القيام به،
because these traditional leaders,
بسبب هؤلاء الزعماء التقليديين
they are already accustomed to the things
أنهم فقد اعتادوا على القيام بهذه الأشياء
that have been there for ages.
التي وجدت منذ عصور
A hard thing to change,
شيء من الصعب تغييره
but a good thing to try.
لكن من الجيد محاولة القيام به
So we tried.
لهذا حاولنا
It was very hard, but we pushed.
لقد كان أمرا صعبا ولكننا كافحنا
And I'm here to say that in my community,
وأنا هنا لأقول أن مجتمعي هو المجتمع الأول
it was the first community after girls
الذي ضغطت فيه الفتيات بشدة
before the age of 18.
قبل بلوغ سن 18
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
In my community,
في مجتمعي
that was the first time a community,
لقد كانت هذه أول مرة يقوم فيها
they had to call the bylaws,
مجتمع بإصدار قوانين
the first bylaw that protected girls
أول قانون يحمي الفتيات
in our community.
في مجتمعنا
We did not stop there.
لم نقف عند هذا الحد
We forged ahead.
ومضينا قُدُماً
We were determined to fight for girls not just in my community,
لقد تمّ تعييننا للنضال من أجل الفتيات ليس فقط في مجتمعنا
but even in other communities.
بل في المجتمعات الأخرى
When the child marriage bill was being presented in February,
عندما تم تقديم مشروع قانون زواج الأطفال في فبراير،
we were there at the Parliament house.
كنّا هناك في غرفة البرلمان
Every day, when the members of Parliament were entering,
كل يوم و عند دخول أعضاء البرلمان
we were telling them, "Would you please support the bill?"
كنا نقول لهم " من فضلك هل يمكنك دعم مشروع القانون "
And we don't have much technology like here,
ولم تكن لدينا تكنولوجيا كما هو الحال هنا
but we have our small phones.
ولكن كانت لدينا هواتفنا الصغيرة
So we said, "Why can't we get their numbers and text them?"
وهكذا قلنا :" لماذا لا نحصل على أرقامهم ثم نراسلهم"
So we did that. It was a good thing.
ثم قمنا بذلك و لقد كان شيئا مفيدا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So when the bill passed, we texted them back,
وهكذا عندما مُرِّر مشروع القانون راسلناهم ثانية
"Thank you for supporting the bill."
"شكرا لكم على دعم مشروع القانون"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And when the bill was signed by the president,
وعندما وقع الرئيس على مشروع القانون
making it into law, it was a plus.
ليصير قانونا، كان هذا قيمة إضافية
Now, in Malawi, 18 is the legal marriage age, from 15 to 18.
الآن في مالاوي يعد سن 18 هو السن القانوني للزواج بعد سن 15
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
It's a good thing to know that the bill passed,
من الجيد أن نعلم أن مشروع القانون تمت المصادقة عليه
but let me tell you this:
لكن دعوني أخبركم بهذا
There are countries where 18 is the legal marriage age,
هناك دول حيث سن 18 هو السن القانوني للزواج
but don't we hear cries of women and girls every day?
لكن ألسنا نسمع صرخات النساء والفتيات كل يوم؟
Every day, girls' lives are being wasted away.
كل يوم تهدر حياة الفتيات
This is high time for leaders to honor their commitment.
هذا هو الأوان للقادة للوفاء بالتزاماتهم
In honoring this commitment,
الوفاء بالاتزامات يعني
it means keeping girls' issues at heart every time.
أن تبقى قضايا الفتيات حاضرة في القلب كل حين
We don't have to be subjected as second,
لا يجب أن يتم اعتبارها كمسألة ثانوية
but they have to know that women, as we are in this room,
لكن يجب أن يعلموا أن النساء كما نحن في هذه الغرفة
we are not just women, we are not just girls,
لسنا مجرد نساء أو مجرد فتيات
we are extraordinary.
نحن خارقات
We can do more.
نستطيع أن نفعل أكثر
And another thing for Malawi,
وهناك شيء آخر لمالاوي
and not just Malawi but other countries:
وليس فقط مالاوي بل الدول الأخرى أيضا
you know how a law is not a law until it is enforced?
لا تكون قوانين حتى يتم فرضها
The law which has just recently passed
القانون الذي تمت المصادقة عليه مؤخرا
and the laws that in other countries have been there,
والقوانين التي في الدول الأخرى هناك
they need to be publicized at the local level,
تحتاج أن يتم إشهارها على المستوى المحلي
at the community level,
على مستوى المجتمع
where girls' issues are very striking.
حيث قضايا الفتيات ملفتة للنظر
Girls face issues, difficult issues, at the community level every day.
تواجه الفتيات قضايا، قضايا صعبة، على مستوى المجتمع المحلي في كل يوم.
So if these young girls know that there are laws that protect them,
حتى تدرك هؤلاء الفتيات الصغيرات أن هناك قوانين تحميهنّ
they will be able to stand up and defend themselves
سيكنّ قادرات على الوقوف والدفاع عن أنفسهن
because they will know that there is a law that protects them.
لأنهن سيعلمن أن هناك قانونا يحميهن
And another thing I would say is that
وهناك شيء آخر أودّ أن أقوله هو أن
girls' voices and women's voices
أصوات الفتيات وأصوات النساء جميلة
are beautiful, they are there,
إنهن هناك
but we cannot do this alone.
ولكن لا يمكننا فعل هذا لوحدنا
Male advocates, they have to jump in,
المدافعون الذكور عليهم الانضمام
to step in and work together.
للتدخل والعمل معاً
It's a collective work.
إنه عمل جماعي
What we need is what girls elsewhere need:
ما نحتاجه هو ما تحتاجه الفتيات في أماكن أخرى
good education, and above all, not to marry whilst 11.
تعليم جيد وقبل كل شيء، عدم الزواج في سن 11
And furthermore,
وعلاوة على ذلك،
I know that together,
أعلم أنه معاَ
we can transform the legal,
يمكننا تغيير الإطار القانوني
the cultural and political framework
الثقافي والسياسي
that denies girls of their rights.
الذي يحرم الفتيات من حقوقهنّ
I am standing here today
أقف هنا اليوم
and declaring that we can end child marriage in a generation.
وأعلن أننا نستطيع إنهاء زواج الأطفال بعد جيل واحد
This is the moment
هذه هي اللحظة
where a girl and a girl, and millions of girls worldwide,
حيث سيكون هناك فتاة وفتاة وملايين الفتيات حول العالم
will be able to say,
قادرات على قول
"I will marry when I want."
"سأتزوج حين أريد"
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا لكم (تصفيق)